<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC9067 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9067.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC7606 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7606.xml">
        <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv.xml">
        <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv-ebit SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv-ebit.xml">
        <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-path-marking-tlv SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-path-marking-tlv.xml">
        <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-bgp-rib-stats SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-bgp-rib-stats.xml">
        <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-model SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-model.xml">

	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_BGP_PDU "TBD1">
	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_EVENT_REASON "TBD2">
	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_POLICY_DISCARD "TBD3">
	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_GROUP "TBD4">
	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_SP "TBD5">
	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_WARNING_BOUND "TBD6">
	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_UPPER_BOUND "TBD7">
	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_MALFORMED_PACKET "TBD8">

	<!ENTITY IANA_REL_CODE_MP_ERRORED_PDU "TBD9">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-grow-bmp-rel-03"
     ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF"
     updates="7854">

    <front>
        <title abbrev="BMP REL">
	    Logging of routing events in BGP Monitoring Protocol (BMP)
	</title>

        <author fullname="Paolo Lucente" initials="P" surname="Lucente">
            <organization>NTT</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Veemweg 23</street>
                    <city>Barneveld</city>
                    <code>3771</code>
                    <region>MT</region>
                    <country>NL</country>
                </postal>
                <email>paolo@ntt.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

	<author fullname="Camilo Cardona" initials="C" surname="Cardona ">
	  <organization>NTT</organization>
	    <address>
	      <postal>
		<street>164-168, Carrer de Numancia</street>
		<city>Barcelona</city>
		<code>08029</code>
		<country>Spain</country>
	      </postal>
              <email>camilo@ntt.net</email>
	    </address>
	</author>

        <date year="2025"/>

        <area>General</area>

        <workgroup>Global Routing Operations</workgroup>
        <keyword>BMP</keyword>
        <keyword>BGP</keyword>
        <keyword>REL</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
		The BGP Monitoring Protocol (BMP) does provision for BGP session event
		logging (Peer Up, Peer Down), state synchronization (Route Monitoring),
		debugging (Route Mirroring) and Statistics messages, among the others.
		This document defines a new Route Event Logging (REL) message type for
		BMP with the aim of covering use-cases with affinity to alerting,
		reporting and on-change analysis.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="Introduction">
            <t>
		As NLRIs are advertised and distributed, policies are applied and, as a
		result, actions are performed on them. Currently, in order to infer the
		outcome of an evaluation process, a comparative analysis needs to be
		performed between Route Monitoring data for two distinct observation
		points of interest, for example Adj-Rib-In pre-policy and post-policy.
		It would be instead more useful if a monitored router could export
		event-driven data with the relevant information.
            </t>
            <t>
		The envisioned use-cases are the most diverse and range from logging
		route filtering to reporting the outcome of validation processes taking
		place on the monitored router, to isolating certain subsets of data
		to be validated offline, to report malformed BGP packets, to broader
		closed-loop operations. 
            </t>
            <t>
		Since no other existing BMP message type does fit the described purpose,
		this document defines a new Route Event Logging (REL) message type that
		is suitable to carry event-driven data and is extensible in nature.
		While the message format is similar to the Route Mirroring message
		type defined in <xref target="RFC7854">RFC 7854</xref> and to the Route
		Monitoring message type as defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">
		TLV support for BMP Route Monitoring and Peer Down Messages</xref>,
		the semantics are different.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Terminology">
            <t>
		The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
		NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
		"MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
		described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>
		<xref target="RFC8174">RFC 8174</xref> when, and only when, they
		appear in all capitals, as shown here.
            </t>
        </section>

	<section title="Route Event Logging (REL) message">
            <t>
		In basic terms a REL message does carry Events. Each Event is
		logically composed by one Event Subject and one or more Event
		Attributes.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The structure of the Route Event Logging message is the same as
		the Route Monitoring message defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">
		TLV support for BMP Route Monitoring and Peer Down Messages</xref>
		where the Per-Peer Header is followed by a BGP Message TLV, one
		indexed Informational TLV and further optional indexed Informational
		TLVs. An example of such structure is available in
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">Section 4.2.1.1 of</xref>.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		One or more Event Subjects are packed as part of a BGP Update PDU.
		The BGP Update PDU <xref target="RFC4271">Section 4.3 of</xref> is
		encoded itself as part of a BGP Message TLV with code point &IANA_REL_CODE_BGP_PDU;
		and index set to zero. Each Event Subject is represented by an
		NLRI carried in the PDU.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The BGP Message TLV may be preceeded and/or followed by indexed
		Informational TLVs that carry Event Attributes, where attributes
		are bound to subjects referring to their positional index within
		the PDU or via a Group TLV as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">
                Section 4.2.1 of</xref>
	    </t>
	    <t>
		Speaking comparatively to other existing message types, REL does
		not require an initial flooding of information as per the state
		synchronization nature of Route Monitoring and does not aim to
		provide a non-state-compressed full-fidelity view of all messages
		received as per the debugging nature of Route Mirroring.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		In the context of BMP REL message, and hence in the reminder of
		this document, the term Event Subject and NLRI will be used
		interchangeably. Also the term Event Attribute and Informational
		TLV will be used interchangeably.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The following sections will describe each component of the REL
		message in more detail. 
	    </t>
	<section title="Per-Peer Header">
	    <t>
		The message does start with a BMP per-peer header as defined in
		<xref target="RFC7854">RFC 7854</xref>, subsequently extended by
		<xref target="RFC8671">RFC 8671</xref> and
		<xref target="RFC9069">RFC 9069</xref> allowing, among the other
		things, to timestamp an Event and set its observation point among
		those defined in BMP.  
	    </t>
	    <t>
		Because the main purpose of the REL message is to log events at
		the time of applying an action, the Peer Flags field - even if
		applied to Adj-Rib-In or Adj-Rib-Out does not have the concept
		of pre- and post-policy. The flags are hence defined as follows:
	    </t>
	    <t>
	    <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|V|A| Reserved  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            ]]></artwork>
	    </figure>
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The V flag and A flag do carry the same meaning as originally defined
		by <xref target="RFC7854">RFC 7854</xref>. The remaining bits are
		reserved for future use. They MUST be transmitted as 0 and their
		values MUST be ignored on receipt. 
	    </t>
	</section>
	<section title="BGP Update PDU">
	    <t>
		The PDU enclosed as part of a BGP Message TLV can be either
		a verbatim copy or artificial, either packed from scratch or
		repacked starting from an existing BGP Update PDU to only
		contain the relevant NLRIs affected by an Event (one or
		multiple). The Event is going to be further described by
		means of Event Attributes by indexed Informational TLVs.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The choice of describing one or multiple Event Subjects via
		a BGP Update PDU is because, on one hand, this does allow to
		not have to invent new encodings for NLRIs, while on the
		other, to support all types and encodings already supported
		by BGP. The advantage being that only minimal new code, on
		both the exporting and the receiving sides, will have to be
		produced. 
	    </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Informational TLVs">
	    <t>
		Informational TLVs in BMP are formalized by the
		intersection of <xref target="RFC7854">RFC 7854</xref>,
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">TLV support for BMP Route
		Monitoring and Peer Down Messages</xref> and
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv-ebit">Support for Enterprise-
		specific TLVs in the BGP Monitoring Protocol</xref>. TLVs in
		a REL message are indexed.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		Contrary to other BMP messages where all Informational TLVs are
		entirely optional, in order for a REL message to be meaningful,
		it MUST contain at least one Event Reason TLV and MAY contain
		other optional attribute TLVs to further characterize the Event.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		A new registry called "Route Event Logging TLVs" is defined and
		is seeded with the TLVs detailed in the following sections.
	    </t>
	    <section title="Event Reason TLV">
		<t>
		    &IANA_REL_CODE_EVENT_REASON; = Event Reason TLV (4 octets).
		    Indicates the IANA-registered reason code describing the type
		    of the event. The following reason codes are defined as part
		    of the "Event Reason TLV" registry:

<figure>
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+--------+------------------------------+
| Value  | Reason			|
+---------------------------------------+
| 0x0000 | Unknown			|
| 0x0001 | Log Action			|
| 0x0002 | Policy Discard		|
| 0x0004 | Validation Fail		|
| 0x0008 | Malformed Packet		|
| 0x0010 | Crossed Warning Bound	|
| 0x0020 | Crossed Upper Bound		|
+--------+------------------------------+

     Table 1: Event Reason Codes ]]></artwork>
</figure>
		</t>
	    </section>
	    <section title="Policy Discard TLV">
		<t>
		    &IANA_REL_CODE_POLICY_DISCARD; = Policy Discard TLV. The value
		    contains a UTF-8 string whose value can be organized freely by an
		    implementation. For example, it may contain the routing policy
		    name that caused the discard; or it may list a sequence of
		    policies and policy nodes traversed; or, more simply, it could
		    be a meaningful return code.
		</t>
		<t>
		    On the escort of <xref target="RFC9067">Section 4 of</xref> and
		    <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-model">YANG Model for Border Gateway
		    Protocol (BGP-4)</xref> it is RECOMMENDED to organize the string
		    as a comma-separated string with the policy definition name being
		    followed by the statement name.
		</t>
	    </section>
	    <section title="Malformed Packet TLV">
		<t>
		    &IANA_REL_CODE_MALFORMED_PACKET; = Malformed Packet TLV. The
		    length is to be set to 2 bytes and the value represents a code
		    giving more information about the specific malforming. Following
		    are the defined code points:
		</t>
		<t>
		<list style="symbols">
			<t>
			Code = &IANA_REL_CODE_MP_ERRORED_PDU;: Errored PDU. The BGP
			message was found to have some error that made it unusable,
			causing it to be treated-as-withdraw <xref target="RFC7606">
			RFC7606</xref>.
			</t>
		</list>
		</t>
	    </section>
	    <section title="Crossed Warning Bound TLV">
		<t>
		    &IANA_REL_CODE_WARNING_BOUND; = Crossed Warning Bound TLV. The
		    length is to be set to 4 bytes and the value to the threshold
		    number of the event.
		</t>
	    </section>
	    <section title="Crossed Upper Bound TLV">
		<t>
		    &IANA_REL_CODE_UPPER_BOUND; = Crossed Upper Bound TLV. The length
		    is to be set to 4 bytes and the value to the threshold number of
		    the event.
		</t>
	    </section>
	</section>
        <section title="Group TLV">
            <t>
		The Group TLV is to form N:M relationships among NLRIs in the BGP
		Update PDU and TLVs of the same Route Event Logging message. This
		TLV has code point &IANA_REL_CODE_GROUP; and follows the definition
		of Group TLV in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">TLV support
		for BMP Route Monitoring and Peer Down Messages</xref>. 
            </t>
	</section>
        <section title="Stateless Parsing TLV">
            <t>
		The Stateless Parsing TLV is to allow parsing of the BGP Update
		PDU independently from a Peer Up message previously received for
		the same BGP session. This TLV can be especially relevant to Route
		Event Logging where the BGP Update PDU is artificial. The TLV has
		code point &IANA_REL_CODE_SP; , it follows the definition of
		Stateless Parsing TLV in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv">TLV
		support for BMP Route Monitoring and Peer Down Messages</xref>
		and uses code point definitions in the Stateless Parsing Registry. 
            </t>
	</section>
	</section>

        <section title="Operational Considerations">
	    <t>
		Route Event Logging messages are event-driven in nature so the general
		recommendation is to use them to report on specific conditions of
		interest in order, for example, to facilitate data mining or avoid
		differential analysis. When the objective is to annotate every
		received or announced NLRI then the recommendation is to use Route
		Monitoring messages with <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-path-marking-tlv">
		BMP Path Marking</xref>.
		As an example consider RPKI validation status: when the objective is
		to report on any validations tatus (ie. valid, invalid and unknown),
		BMP Path Marking should be used; when the objective is instead to
		report only invalids then Route Event Logging with Validation Fail
		Event Reason should be used.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		There exist a definite overlap between Route Event Logging when used
		to report Malformed Packet and the use-cases for Route Mirroring where
		Errored PDUs may be sampled for reporting. From implementors perspective,
		if one wants to implement broader event-driven notifications and does not
		want to offer exact mirroring of monitored BGP sessions without state
		compression it may be adviceable to prefer implementing Route Event
		Logging message type over Route Mirroring. From a collector perspective,
		similarly, one may want to activate distinct BMP feeds for event logging
		and route collection and, also in this case, reporting malformed packets
		via Route Event Logging message type may be preferrable over Route
		Mirroring.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		Crossed warning bound and crossed upper bound events refer to
		the received route thresholds that can be configured according
		to <xref target="RFC4271">Section 6.7 of</xref>. Also the stats
		counters part of these events is being addressed by the <xref
		target="I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-bgp-rib-stats">Definition For New BMP
		Statistics Type</xref> document.
	    </t>
	</section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
		It is not believed that this document adds any additional security
		considerations.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
		TBD
	    </t>
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>

    <references title="References">
		&RFC2119;
		&RFC8174;

		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7606.xml"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7854.xml"?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8671.xml"?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9067.xml"?>
                <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9069.xml"?>

		&I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv;
		&I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-tlv-ebit;
		&I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-path-marking-tlv;
		&I-D.ietf-grow-bmp-bgp-rib-stats;
		&I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-model;
    </references>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
            <t>
		The authors would like to thank Jeff Haas, Luuk Hendriks,
		Ruediger Volk, Ahmed Elhassany, Thomas Graf and Ben Maddison for
		their valuable input. The authors would also like to thank Mike
		Booth for his review.
            </t>
    </section>

    </back>
</rfc>
